[D. Evans] The purpose of Backus-Naur Form is to be able to precisely describe
巴科斯范式的目的是为了用一种简单而概要的方式
exactly the language in a way that's very simple and very concise.
来精确地描述语言
So each rule has the form like this where on the left side there's a non-terminal.
这种语法的表达 像左边这个非终止符
Non-terminal means something that we're not finished with.
非终止符表示我们还没完成
All the words written in blue in the grammar are non-terminals.
所有蓝色的字符都是非终止符
Sometimes they're written with brackets around them.
有时候他们是用尖括号括起来
I've just used blue to distinguish the non-terminals like this.
我们用蓝色来表示非终止符
Then there's an arrow, and then on the right side there's a replacement.
这是一个箭头 右边就是可替换项
The replacement can be anything.
这个可以是任何东西
It can be a sequence of non-terminals like here.
可以是一系列非终止符
Sentence can be replaced with subject followed by verb followed by object.
句子用主谓宾的顺序
It can be 1 non-terminal like here.
可以是一个非终止符
It can also be a terminal, and the terminals I've written in black.
也可以是终止符 ——用黑色字符来表示
What's special about the terminals is they never appear on the left side of a rule.
终止符一定不能放在左边
Once we get to a terminal, we're done, we're finished.
遇到终止符我们就要停止了
There's nothing else we can replace it with.
而且不能用别的替换
So all the rules have this form.
所有的语法都是这个形式
We can form a sentence by starting from some non-terminal,
我们可以用一些非终止符开始写句子
usually whichever one is written at the top left--
一般是从左上角开始
in this case the one I called sentence.
这里我们叫它句子
And then by following the rules we keep replacing non-terminals with their replacements
然后我们可以接着替换这些非终止符
until we're left with only terminals.
直到遇到终止符
Here's an example starting from sentence using the grammar above.
这是一个语法句子的例子
We can start with sentence.
我们从句子开始
We only have 1 rule to choose from where sentence is on the left side,
只要从左边找出合适的词类来组成句子
so we're going to replace sentence with subject, verb, object.
我们要用主语 谓语 宾语来替换句子
Now we have a lot of choices.
现在我们有很多选择
We can pick any of the non-terminals we have left.
我们可以用任何非终止符
Find a rule where that non-terminal is on the left side.
从左边的非终止符中寻找合适的词类
We can pick any of the rules where it's on the left side and do the replacement.
我们可以选择左边的任何词类做替代
So I'm going to start with the left one. We'll pick subject.
让我从左边开始 我们先选择主语
We only have 1 replacement rule for subject.
我们只有一个可替换词类来表示主语
We can replace subject with noun.
我们用名词代替主语
The others stay like they are, so we still have verb and we still have object.
此外 我们还要有动词和宾语
Now we can keep going.
我们继续
We can pick the first one again.
我们换一个
It's still a non-terminal, so we can still do replacements.
还是一个非终止符 我们可以继续替换
With noun we've got 3 choices.
有三个名词可以选
We can pick any one of those choices.
我们可以任选一个
I'm going to pick the first one. We'll replace noun with the terminal I.
我就用第一个了 用“我”来替换名词
Now we've got a terminal. We're done with that replacement.
这里是终止符 我们的替代完成了
Verb and object stay the same.
动词和宾语也一样
I'm running out of space, so I'm not going to write them again
这没地方了 我就不再写一遍了
because now we can use rules to replace verb.
我们用这些词类来代替动词
As a separate step we're going to find a rule that matches verb.
我们看看那些词可以用来当动词
We have 2 choices. I'll pick the second one and replace verb with like.
有两个 我们就用第二个“喜欢”来替代动词
We still have object.
还需要宾语
Object is a non-terminal, so we have to keep replacing it until we're done.
宾语也是非终止符 意味着还没完成我们继续
We have 1 rule for object. We can replace object with noun.
我们有一个词类来代表宾语 我们用名词来当宾语
Now we have 3 rules for noun. I'm going to pick the second rule and replace noun with Python.
我们有三个词是名词 我们用第二个 Python 好了
What I've done here is what's called a derivation.
我们这里做的叫推导
A derivation just means starting from some non-terminal,
一个推导意味着从非终止符开始
follow the rules to derive a sequence of terminals.
按照词类来构成
We're done when we have only terminals left
最终左侧只剩终止符
and we can derive a sentence in the grammar.
我们就用语法构成了一个句子
In this case we produced the sentence I like python,
这里我们的句子是“我爱 Python”
but there are lots of other sentences we could have produced
我们还可以造很多句子
starting from the same non-terminal if we pick different rules to follow.
一样的从非终止符开始 用不同的词类来替换